Yeah. Right. [clears throat] So, yeah.
Uh, today I thought of going through
the, uh, couple of short suitors
that are sort of related, a bit of a
overlap in terms of a
theme. Uh, one is Angut 313,
Apai Kasuta, and then the other one is
Angutra 3 112 before that, but we'll do
it after, which is Duty Nidana. So,
So,
so I'll [clears throat] just read
through them first because they're quite
they're fairly short and then we can we
can go through the points things that
come up in questions. So, Apayasuta says
because there are these three who are
destined for deprivation, destined for
hell, having not abandoned this. What
three? One who is not celibate yet has
undertaken the claim of being celibate.
one who without grounds accuses a person
who is celibate of not being celibate
and the one who is such a speaker and
holder of such a view that there is no
fault in central pleasures because of
that view he falls headfirst into
central pleasures. These bikers are the
three three types of people who are
destined for deprivation, destined for
hell, having not abandoned this um
uh because there are these three origins
for the arising of action. What three?
With regard to past phenomena that are
grounds for desire and lust, desire
arises. With regard to future phenomena,
there the grounds for desire and lust.
Desire arises. With regard to present
phenomena, there are grounds for desire
and lust. Desire arises.
So how big does desire arise with regard
to past future present phenomena that
are grounds for desire and lust? Well,
with reference to past, future present
phenomena that are grounds for desire
and lust. One repeatedly thinks and
ponders them along the same lines with
the mind.
While one is repeatedly thinking and
pondering along the same lines with
their mind desire arises when desire has
arisen one becomes feted to those
phenomena and this be who I call a feta
which is the last of the mind the mind's
lust thus beu desire arises with reference to
thus beu desire arises with reference to
the past future present phenomena the
grounds for desire and lust to arise
um so then Buddha goes and explains the
opposite saying because there these
three origins for the non-arising of
action. What three? Well, with regard to
the past phenomena, they're the grounds
for desire and last. Desire does not
arise. With regard to the future phenomena, the
With regard to the future phenomena, the
grounds for desire and last, desire does
not arise. With regard to present
phenomena, the grounds for desire and
last, desire does not arise. The point
being uh removal of desire equals uh
non-action. Removal of karma, removal of
action. We'll see that later obviously
get into more detail. So how because
desire not arise with regard to the
past, future, present phenomena that the
grounds for desire and lust. Uh well,
one understands the subsequent results
of past, future, present phenomena that
are grounds for desire and lust. Having
known the subsequent results, one turns
away from them. Having turned away,
having penetrated with the mind, one
sees through with wisdom. Thus, desire
does not arise with regard to past
phenomena that are grounds for desire
and lust. And that's beu is the origin
for the non-arising of action.
Right? So yeah, if you go back to the um
to the beginning to the first suta
and um
the the three types of people
that are destined for deprivation.
Uh so you could see that what's what's
in common
what's in common to these um individuals
put it that way
uh would be um like a level of of of um
perversion of the truth let's put it
that way a certain amount of that kind
of existential discrepancy that they
maintained which is what constitutes the
the the weight of of depravity the
weight of the of their karma that will
make them you know go to hell and so on.
So it's not just to say like oh anybody
that engages inuality is destined for
for hell but also of course it it's it's
it is pointing in that direction. I mean
that's kind of the whole Mara's trap and
taming of the senses and everything the
Buddha talks about in virtually every
other suta.
So, but obviously in this case it's like
the the the three kind of um obvious and
you know not even so subtle types of uh
intentional choice that results in
perversion of the obvious.
So the the degrees of perversion
determine the the the depth of hell if
we can put it that way. So you could see
like what's what's in common to these
things. Um as I've asked before, it's um
it's kind of so you have a person well
say you have a person who is who who who
hears about oh sensuality is bad. So
sensuality should at least be
curbed, moderated, kept in check. You shouldn't
moderated, kept in check. You shouldn't
just take it for granted and blindly
engage with it. And then they, you know,
maybe want to want to do it even
further. It's like, no, I really want to
I I see the problem of sensual desires.
I really want to free myself from it. So
they take on the vow of celibacy to
train to train in in abandoning of of
those fundamental deeply rooted desires,
but then they break it. But now it's
that choice of perversion that comes up.
choice of discrepancy would be when they
break it,
they do not uh confess it, they do not
admit it, they do not rec well they they
don't dare to like basically acknowledge
the fault. So they pretend they're still
doing it and it might not even be that
um say like a a person like kind of
pre-plans that oh I will say I'm
celebrated and not it might be that
they're lying to themselves. So it might
be like a subtle kind of bad faith of oh
yeah no I didn't mean to I am still
celibate and they genuinely believe
they're celibate
while actually they keep breaking and
contradicting that very very claim very
state of being.
So it's not just like oh I say I'm
celibate and I lied or something once or
twice uh and then you know I saw the
amended my ways and so on. It's more
like on the level of
lying to yourself and living in that
mode of not actually being celibate but
convincing yourself that you are. So you
see it's not like um
in and of itself obviously that doesn't
harm anybody so to speak. So, it's not
like killing somebody or stealing or
lying, but you could see the weight of
that existential uh deception,
self-imposed, self-created,
self-maintained that it's going to
completely like mess up your chitta in a
sense of like what um where it will head
to and what it can do about its own
state. If you're if you're able to
maintain such a degree of of self
delusion, you are heading downwards so
to speak like in terms of your views, in
terms of your actions and so on. Uh but
again, it's on the basis of your choice,
which means a person can technically
start choosing to become transparent and
question and and re-evaluate what they
believe themselves are or not. So it can
be undone. in 100 words. Then you have
the second type of person who without
grounds as it says accuses a person who
celibate of not being celibate. So that
would be like a you you could see you
could ask yourself like why would
somebody do that? So what scenario would
would kind of prompt somebody to do that
to to say oh you know he who is celibate
I'm I want to accuse him of not being
celibate. I want others to think that
that um he's not celibate. Now of course
you could have some like individual
instances oh because they fell out or
something but this speaks like on the
level of the principle of somebody
engaging with the as we can see with the
third one engaging on the level of the
view that oh I'm not celibate but I
undertaken the claim of being celibate
and I believe I'm celibate but actually
my actions keep contradicting it and I'm
turning a blind eye to it. The second
one would be oh celibacy basically
frightens me. The idea of giving up
sensuality is like the abyss like how
the other when that layman was talking
to the Buddha he says when when the
household is here about restraint it's
like a sudden abyss. So it's like that's
that's fine in and of itself like
experiencing that it's it's normal like
somebody who depends on sensuality
hearing that they have to abandon it
that will be the most natural kind of
response. Oh my god, this is
frightening. And that's not a problem.
The problem is what view you then choose
to pretty much develop and fall into
so that you obscure and cover up and
protect yourself from that fear and
justify uh not actually doing anything
about it. So you could see how then
somebody would hear about syllabus, hear
about the peril of sensuality,
uh hear about that if you want to make
merit and be reborn in heavens and so on
and believes in that like they need to
you know put a lid on the the the the
degree of animal behavior they engage
engage with and also the reasons behind
engaging with. So it can't be just
careless. Oh, it's allowed and stuff
like that. But then you could see like,
oh, that feels like too much of a task.
And then the the easiest the first sort
of protocol would be, oh, blame those
that are able to do it because you kind
of deep down feel like you're not able
to do it. You don't want to do it. You
don't want to have to go through it. So
let me find fault in those that are
doing it and say, "No, even they can't
do it. Nobody can really do it. They
just claim they do it." and you're not
really even care about them that much.
You're just doing that
um
you're just doing that to protect
yourself like to put the view outside
that can be shared by others and
partaken others and affirmed by others
acknowledged by others validated by
others uh that oh yeah nobody can really
do it. Thus I am exempted from feeling
that I must also do it which then
increases that initial fear that I
experienced when I heard about the sense
strain in the abyss.
And then the third person would be like
taking that view
even like say not directing directing it
in anybody personally to justify their
non-doing but then just pertaining
making a statement and developing a
belief on the level of a view which is
that no sensuality is not an obstacle.
basically. So, uh they don't even try to
take it on and then fail and maybe
delude themselves and maybe rectify
that. They don't even try to like oh let
me undermine those that claim it's
possible uh and say that it's not possible. No,
uh and say that it's not possible. No,
they just say now the whole view that
sensuality is a problem uh it's not
really a problem. So there is no fault
in sensual pleasure and that's why this
one is the worst actually. Like you can
see it's the most personal in a sense.
It only really involves you. Doesn't
involve your public statement, how
others perceive you. Doesn't inform what
others do. But it's actually the worst
because it kind of pertains to self-d
delusion and obscuring and covering up
the most obvious which is that you know
if you're honest even of the most
hiddenistic person you know in the
moments of their clarity
could see the the the kind of the
deprivation the unpleasantness the the
the the unpleasant drive and force of of
their own [snorts] desires that they
that they're just subjected to. you
know, you would get fatigued, you would
get put off if you just honestly look at
it. Now, of course, you know, you might
decide to ignore it and most people
would and so on, but that's one thing is
to, okay, I can't deal with this. I
don't want to do anything about it. But
another thing is like, oh no, let me
develop a view
that will soothe and comfort my own
self-imposed delusion. they will then
maintain that whole kind of uh uh sense
of ease that I have in terms of oh I
don't have to do with this I don't have
to deal with this I don't have to go
through restraint withdrawal because
there is no fault in this anyway and
that's what it says because of that view
they will become even more careless in
regard to sensuality they would have
been otherwise even without having even
without say being celibate and and
withdrawn so somebody who kind of it's
it's on a somewhat has some sort of
recognition of yeah, you know, it's it's good to
of yeah, you know, it's it's good to
sort of at least moderate your s
sensuality and engagement in how much
time you you you sort of dwell on it. Um
how far you let your mind take you. It's
like yeah, it's probably good to sort of
restrain it a bit even in the worldly
terms. We're not even talking about the
practice of the dharma now because it's
just about, you know, whether you're
going in state of deprivation or you're
going upwards in a in a in a in in in
heavens or better rewards. So it's like
without like as I said you without
abandoning sensuality but at least not
completely covering up kind of the
obvious course immediately verifiable
nature of when desire arises that it's
actually unpleasant and that whole thing
uh you won't be as bad because it it
will at least you keep you somewhat in
check when it comes to if you actually
after having heard that sensuality is
bad and stuff you actually choose to go
the other way and double down and
convince yourself that no there is no
fault in sensuality. You start to
override even that basic recognition
which now removed any breaks you had
which means now you would really not
think twice about engaging in sensual
pleasures because you have successfully
convinced yourself that there's
absolutely no fault in it. So that's why
this is on the level of yeah you're
destined for the states of deprivation.
Um so that's why it's like um
um it's not that you know say a lay
practitioner somebody who wants to
practice um is destined for the state of
um is destined for the state of
deprivation simply by not being celibate
or something.
It's like no you need to one thing is to
kind of train and develop and fail and
try again through that transparency and
recognition with the practices. Another
thing is to just like faultf find uh so
to undermine stuff that you heard from
others that you should do in terms of
practice. Oh no, well look, they don't
do it themselves. As if that kind of
absolves you from doing it. Uh or even
to say no, there's actually this doesn't
need to be abandoned. There is no
problem with this. um which as I said
overrides the basic recognition and
obviously in the case of somebody who is
familiar with the sutras it's kind of
even worse because they override what
the Buddha himself said in so many
sutras you know it's like one thing is to say
you know it's like one thing is to say
oh yeah maybe you know it feels too much
now maybe I need to work for it
gradually and then start working towards
right restraint right intention and and
and and purifying your behavior another
thing is to say oh no no that's that was
just for the monks that doesn't apply to
me yet at the same time I claim I follow
the Buddhist teaching. So it's just you
could see like the layers and layers of
extra kind of perversions and
contradictions added to the obvious
truth like to obvious anybody honest
enough to admit through the sudas would
arrive at that conclusion.
So that's why it's like um
um this is kind of useful. I included
this suta because like leading to the
next one that that I that I wanted to
talk about it was kind of just to
recognize that um the training
of like freeing yourself from your
desires being able to contain them and
free yourself. It's not like something
you just can adhere to externally. Even
if as said before you keep all the
precepts perfectly but don't make the
effort to actually train in those
principles, you'll still remain bound
with the same desires. You're just not
acting out of them. And that's good. As
the Buddha said, even if somebody spends
the rest of the monk spends the rest of
his life just crying with pains of
restraint, but doesn't go back to those
desires, he'll still heading upwards.
He's still heading to heavens at least
if he doesn't get the right view. Um but
obviously you know more needs to be done
and that's that whole training that we
often talk about recognizing your
intentions and stuff. It's not just a
question of saying no blanket no to
everything that your mind ever wants.
So that's like the second suta like the
the three origins for the arising of
action and it's like when the desire
arises for the past phenomena, future phenomena
for the past phenomena, future phenomena
or the present phenomena. So that is
what's considered an action. So acting
out of a desire it what it's what kama
is as we said before.
So and how does the desire arise? Well,
when say a phenomena concerning past,
future or present, doesn't matter what
thoughts or what perceptions would have
come up that can serve as grounds for
desire and lust. And you know, certain
things universally serve for as grounds
for desire and lust for everybody. For
different people there's going to be
some kind of idiosyncratic variations
like something will not be lustful for
somebody due to their own history
culture upbringing but for somebody else
will be due to your past actions as well
like what you've been choosing so far
and so on the lust grows and
proliferates and gets associated with
new things or disassociated from some
other things. So the point is not to
examine the nature of those phenomena.
The point is to recognize whatever
phenomena has a reason. Is there a
corresponding possibility of lust? Is
there an incentive? Is there a pressure
towards lust? That already qualifies
enough. You don't need to know more
about the type and the content and how
this phenomena came to be and so on.
That's all pretty much irrelevant.
So
um
with reference to past, future, present,
fant grounds for desire and last one
repeatedly thinks and ponders them along
the same lines with the mind. So that's
the key here. You have perceptions
arising whether saitance melt touches
thoughts in regard to past, future or
present doesn't matter. As I said, they
come up with a with a with an offer,
with a promise, with a with a push in a
certain directions. Even if you don't
necessarily know where or what
specifically your desire wants you to do
or or or or have or or perceive, you can
already tell it's it wants it's going to
be something. It's sending you in a
direction. So, the pressure it's already
felt. That's uh like unmistakable. You
you already know that. So whenever
something pressuring arises that it's
sort of kind of pushing for the thoughts
for the momentum behind the thoughts oh
yeah let me let me go with this and
think about it that's what this means
that one repeatedly thinks and ponders
them along the same lines so it's not
like oh I something arises and I reflect
on it or I just broadly abstractly think
about it. It's like no when it's coming
out of that thread of compulsion even
before it's defined as compulsion
necessarily because the pressure it's
already a form of compulsion. So are
your thoughts
uh past future present phenomena doesn't
matter connected? Are they are they are they
connected? Are they are they are they
infused and are they sort of exhibiting
that pressure on you to continue
thinking along the lines that they
presented themselves with? If it's you
know positive um uh positive in the
sense of like desirable agreeable to
think more ponder engage with it speak
about it uh uh expose your senses to it
and so on or even voice the same way uh
in the opposite like if it's if it's
aversive same the pressure arises for
aversion to go along the lines along the
lines of aversion that's already implied
that that phenomena is pushing you
towards so that's that middle ground at the
so that's that middle ground at the
right level. I often talk about that
people need to discern and the only way
to discern that is to first stop
automatically acting out of these
things. Acting out of desire towards
more of it and then acting out of a
version towards trying to get rid of the
entire experience. In other words,
trying to deny, remove, distract
yourself away, concentrate yourself away
from the present phenomena because you
don't see the difference between present
phenomena that are grounds for desire
and the actual desire and lust. That is
pretty much your doing. How is your
doing? Well, you repeatedly allow, think
and ponder, choose to go along the lines
that they offer.
So what happens when you don't go along
the lines that they offer? Well, the
lines remain there, not followed. The
pressure remains there, dried up.
That's how you see through it.
So while one is repeatedly thinking and
pondering them along the same lines,
desire will grow. it will arise it will
become even more associated with those
phenomena and mind the animal will be completely
and mind the animal will be completely
fattered by that bond. Then whatever you
do in response to that uh go on a
retreat uh sense deprivation
all of that is to manage the past future
present phenomena and possibility of
their arising. None of that addresses
the mind's lust the desire towards those
things. It's like starving the animal.
You cannot keep it still. You cannot
train it. You cannot teach it to only
eat the right food. All you can do it,
let it eat or completely starve it. And
then you starve it on a retreat on a
super intense concentration nostril
watching practice
or whatever whatever other kind of
methods of of denial you might engage
with. But then when that wears out, and
it will, the animal still has no
knowledge, no difference between eating
things that are not the ground for
desire and eating things and engaging
with things at the ground for desire
because the mind needs to learn that.
So that's how desire arises and then the
Buddha goes to describe how desire does
not arise. Well, one understands the
subsequent results of past and future,
present phenomena that are ground for
desire and lust. How because does desire
not to arise with not arise with regard
to past future present phenomena they're
a ground for it well one understands the
subsequent results they're the ground
for it so one now understands the
implicit results that follow from this
that are implicit in it not like I have
to go through subsequent results to
understand this no no one presently
understands that
and that's how one turns away from this
desire now that's what the suta
describes not It's like, yeah, go
through it until you're jaded and then
you can tell yourself, see, I'm
desireless now. No, you're just tired.
Your your animal is asleep cuz he got
what he wanted. Maybe even sick cuz he
over ate. But again, that will go away
and it going to go back to the same
things cuz he hasn't learned. So, it's
understanding the implicit results
[snorts] of the phenomena that the
ground for desire and lust right now,
understanding what they imply way before
you end up there.
That's how the mind turns away from
them. That's how desire will not uh
grow. It will diminish and it will not
become associated now with those
phenomena. So the practical examples of this would
So the practical examples of this would
be well pretty much any reflection done
rightly. So you know the reflections
like a sub reflection or even as I said
even um like in terms of the ill will
and so on you could you could undermine
the same thing if you also well if you
first don't follow immediately along the
lines of the pressure uh along the well
the lines that pressure kind of um
offers you
uh to think about to follow along. You
say no to that but then you don't deny
the pressure because again you need to
as the suta says later you need to
penetrate through it you need to
understand it not just replace it with
something else that suits you. So the
problem is not past future present
phenomena the ground for lust. The
problem is that whenever they're present
the mind cannot but help it fall into
lust. So you want to teach the mind in
regard to those prompts in regard to
those things not just get rid of them
have something else there. So the
subsequent results, the implicit results
could be anything from like well as a
sut says like in some sort of like the
danger of sensuality is having to work
and plow fields, having to earn, having
to protect what you earn, being exposed
to the elements, having to deal with
other people. Those are the dangers.
It's like yeah, they are they are the
implicit results. Even if it's like
we're looking 20 years later but
whatever works on different times if
that's what your desire aims well those
are will be the subsequent implicit
results that become revealed when you
don't follow along the lines
automatically. If on the other hand um you don't think
If on the other hand um you don't think
that far you could bring it to the
immediate such as the natural disgust of
the body say in terms of the sexual
desire uh which is already like a form of
uh which is already like a form of
consumption
like not acting out of it. Not trying to
deny that there is a again mind leading
towards lust. um not following the
thoughts, fantasies
that are outlined there, the directions
of those not allowing in the center
stage as I said in previous talks and
then instead choosing to think again
within the same setup of past, future,
present phenomena ground for desire, you
choose to think the non effectually
non-desiring aspects
at the same time. So concurrently, so
one of the implicit results of a more
immediate kind would be consuming or
engaging with a form that's objectively
disgusting. And you would do that if you
ignore the disgusting aspects. But if
you have the disgusting aspects there
again, not as a replacement
to the past, future present phenomena,
but as a as a kind of additional
uh context.
So I'm not trying to replace, I'm just
trying to include it at the same time
and let the mind decide.
And that's the key here. That's that
right balance. The right balance is
setting up a suba setting up non- ill
will not as a as a replacement as a
force to replace and change the mind but
as something so that even enough with
the the the the pressures towards lust
or towards ill will even enough so that
the mind can see both equally and then
it will naturally actually prefer then
oh yeah this is not desirable because
the only reason things are desirable is
because the non-desiring non-desirable
aspects are not are ignored.
or are thought about after as an
afterthought not presented and
maintained on the same right level.
So it doesn't kind of seep through the
the the association that oh any desire
any involvement with the desirable sex
sight sight sounds smell taste touches
is inseparable. It's the it's the same
thing as these disgusting organs and
brain and and bile and excrement and all
these other reflections that you know
that monks are encouraged to do or
anybody wants to free themselves from
sensuality should be doing. But again,
not as a as a as an empty practice,
mantra mechanical that you go through
uh but as something that sure you might
think of it like when you have no
desire. Think about it. Think about it
in that really palpable sense of these
uh disgusting aspects. But the point is
so that you can be able to that when the
mind is [sighs and gasps] aroused or
pressured with the desire, you're able
to also bring up this context and keep
it there for the mind until the mind
comes down and it will. That's how you
know I don't need to get rid of the
mind. I don't need to destroy the world.
I don't need to pull my eyes out to
never see anything agreeable. I just
need to never willingly choose to go
along the default lines of the pressure
and then be lazy in terms of bringing up
the other counterpart the other side of
the same coin at the same time just to
that extent I don't need to force it
further because you might feel like you
start bringing up the assuba to the
right extent and you see like the mind
just completely losing the desire and
then you feel like okay let me push it
harder let me bring even more now it's
like no now you're falling falling from
the tune, you're falling from the right
music. Now it's getting too tight.
That's where you have to stay patient.
It's like, "No, no, no. I'll keep it
only." But then the mind will come up.
Yeah, the mind will come up again and
I'll again set up the right balance and
maintain it until the mind learns that
this thing that it wants is actually
this thing. It's just the one aspect of
this fundamentally
repulsive, fundamentally non-desirable
in that way thing. That's it. That's to
the extent that you need to do it. So
that's how and that's also see an
implicit result like if I now allow
these thoughts or desires the implicit
result of that is me consuming the
excrement me being in contact with bile
me with being factually like in touch
with things that I wouldn't touch
otherwise. Even as that other suta says
when that man was offering his daughter
to the Buddha. So I wouldn't touch that
form with a foot with my foot like like
what do you want me to do with it? So
it's like you factually wouldn't do it
if it's presented like a like a like a
non like you know organs bile the the
stuff that body is made of. So that's
another subsequent result of my
engagement is me actually being in
contact being in touch being bound with
with stuff that I actually in isolation
would deem repulsive would dem like what
was I thinking type of thing. So you
want to have that context present when
there is that offer of oh think along
these lines just relax and go along this
give the mind the fantasy it wants or
you know if you're not engaging in the
bodily or verbal behavior but still now
the fantasy becomes the expression of it
so it's like no I got to counter that as
well by instead of going along those
lines I'll think I I'll maintain these
lines I'll maintain these perceptions
just again I'm not expecting any
instantaneous kind of insight and and
resolution I'm just keeping be there to
make sure the mind knows that well if
you want this this has to be there with
it cannot not be there
and that's the diligence that's the
practice that one does that then results
in there will be no desire and lust
spreading growing and the arisen one
will diminish
without you needing to deal distract
yourself away concentrate yourself away
from any past future present traumas
memories preferences doesn't matter all
of that is addressed presently ly
through diminishing and uprooting the
desire towards it, towards having it,
towards dealing with it, towards getting
rid of it, towards whatever basically
whatever direction your mind wants to
take.
So, let me just see [clears throat]
were there any more questions.
So yeah, I think I think I kind of
mentioned like a touch upon it maybe
when I spoke about it more but basically
yeah like so why for example
when it says past phenomena future
phenomena present phenomena why is the
only way of penetrating them
understanding them here and now in the
present because desire and lust are always in
because desire and lust are always in
the present.
Like if you think about your past desire
and lust.
If now you have desire on account of you
thinking about your past engagement with
phenomena and objects of desire and
lust, that is your present desire.
Same thinking about the future,
planning, you want it now.
That's your present desire. That's your
action. So thinking about the future is
not a problem. Past that you've been
through that you cannot change is not a
problem. having still desire or aversion
even now that's where the connection is
still maintained that's where the
problem still exists so you you remove
the desire now
you would have overcome your entire past
doesn't matter how wild would have been
could have been and so on same with the
future doesn't matter how insecure or or
or uncertain it won't affect you now
because there is no desire to interfere
with it there is no desire to change it
there is no desire to to address it
because well you understood that the
problem was never in those phenomena
that are ground for lust. The problem
was in your own currently maintained
desire towards it. So I did ask like
what does it mean to penetrate it with
the mind? And I actually I answered it.
It's obviously like people people answer
that right. It's like what means that
the animal needs to understand it. It's
not just about you figuring it out. And
that's why [clears throat]
another kind of um say
another reason why um I often say
contemporary practices meditation
techniques actually take you in a
completely different direction in in
opposite direction of where you should
be going. Uh anytime you think well
concentration helps and helps me focus,
helps me calm down.
All of that pertains to you and your
choice of attention. What you choose to
attend, what you choose to ignore. Um
none of that results in animal actually
getting the right message
in animal actually understanding for
itself because your focusing away your
because your focusing away your
concentration aims as I said already
aims at dealing uh with phenomena that
are ground for lust aims with u uh kind
of uh avoiding sight sounds smells
touches and thoughts that ground for
last past. How do I deal with past
traumas? Well, you know, practice
mindfulness, body sensations, focus here
and now. Don't think about it. Or often
as you hear in the contemporary
tradition, it's like, well, you know,
um, future is not yet. So, stop thinking
about it. Don't dwell on the past. Just
let go of it. As if future are the
problem. Those thoughts are the problem.
So, how do I deal with it? I deal with
it by concentrating on the present
moment, present nostril. When that's not
enough, you need to increase the present
moment. You need to make it even more
specific. So it's not incidental that all the
So it's not incidental that all the
abidamas and and similar views similar
meditation techniques and practices
evolved in that direction to the point
of now you are seeing imaginary kalapas
that don't really exist. They exist in
your fantasy as the real measures of
objective experience that is subatomic
level of like your perception is just
complete nonsense that would have
exactly the same direction of how you
would have started. let me just focus on
here and now and not think about these
things because I don't know how to deal
with the pressure when it arises. Yet
the suta clearly says how to deal with
it. Don't follow it along. Doesn't say
concentrate away until those phenomena
never come again. No, don't follow along
and instead think about the implicit
results that are already known.
maintain them diligently within that
framework and desire will subside and
you would have risen above the past and
the future and everything else because
you would have been now fully
disconnected from it. So that's the
point to recognize like any time any any
pretty much anytime you engage with a
practice whatever technique whatever method
whatever technique whatever method
whatever sort of practice you're doing
but if that is rooted in dealing with
phenomena that are ground for lust if
it's aiming at them
you are not seeing the mind you're not
seeing the basis for training the mind
which means the mind will not get the
right message the mind will not
penetrate through what it needs to
penetrate because you keep basically
pointing at the wrong things as the as
the root of the problem.
So when it says the mind penetrates
means okay. So you would have stopped
trying to deal with past future present
phenomena the ground for last as the
problem drew a line to not give in by body by
drew a line to not give in by body by
speech mentally started being diligent
to not follow the choices of oh I'll
think along them along with what they
offer even if it's just a little bit
like no instead of thinking along I'll
bring up something else to be there with
that pressure so so that the mind
remembers like oh this is what's waiting
for me when I go there
and that as I said can be an immediate
kind of disgust in regard to what's
wanted or can be like a broad
implications of where this leads to
whatever helps the mind sit back down
whatever helps the dog that jumped up
ready to go sit back down and reconsider
the direction he wants to go
yeah it was like that um kind of
reminded me I think it was that forest
masters that book or something I think
I'm mentioning once I think I finished
it but it was like these kind of uh
stories about the Thai monks of the time
and I think one of the
Ajuna contemporaries or something like
that. He was like um living in the
forest but then his head monk called him
back to go back to the temple to do his
duties and then he was stuck there for
like over a year and the mind just got
infected with sensuality fantasies cuz
he was just like living in a busy
Bangkok place with like women around and
stuff and then he was like like really
kind of on the verge of just disrobing
and started fantasizing you know get a
good Bangkok wife start a business
together he has all these ideas start a
family but then he [laughter]
that's obviously worked for him and you
could see but then he was like oh well
let me take that further. So it was
like, "Oh yeah, okay. So I could
distrobe and, you know, find a wife,
maybe there already some candidates, do
this, do that. Um, have a have buy a
house, have a good income, then we'll
probably, you know, start arguing, start
disagreeing, she'll be like this, I
would be like that, then we'll probably
divorce, then probably this, they
probably that." And then his whole
desire went around in a full loop and
came back to like, "Oh, I might as well
not go down that path." which kind of
bought him some time until I I think
look I don't whatever the story is
Ajaman passed through and then took him
with him type of thing and that kind of
saved him but it is already implicit and
even if you stop say when there is no
acute desire you can think in those
broad terms and it does not necessarily
mean it will be abstract or inaccurate
if those broad terms start pertaining to
the actual implications of your desire
so said you have to work there you have
to kind of not just go through the
motions of auba or something but
actually Oh, okay. Let me
philosophically consider this.
Where would this lead me? Like, do do I
already do I already not know? Have I
not tried it before? Have I not done it
before? What are the implications of me
committing to this? And really allow
those answers to sink in. That's already
a form of reathering a certain context
that can that can help the mind from
just automatically following along the
lines. So seeing a divorce as a as a implicit
So seeing a divorce as a as a implicit
subsequent inescapable
outcome separation from any type of
pairing, it's already like, oh,
it does devalue it quite a bit if you
allow it to sink in. If you make the
effort to actually reflect and think
about it and have those thoughts, those
context present, enduring. So that's how
the mind penetrates things. Now it's
your own mind, the animal that doesn't
want that. So when those phenomena come
up that pressure there was pretty much
your own animal untamed animal going
immediately leaping up at the
possibility lessens
because the animal already sees what's
implicit because you've shown it enough.
You haven't been trying to replace those
things blindly and deal with those
phenomena or concentrate away or not
experience them ever again. No, instead
when they came you broadened the
context. You really showed it what it's
like. Same like you know a child wants
to I don't know stick its hand into a
power power in a plug you can tell it no
and for some children maybe yeah that
will be enough but somebody know they
won't see it so you show them what
happens you show them the implicit result of
you show them the implicit result of
what will happen if you do it
so it's like that's what I mean like you
need to make these connections not just
abstractly go but really like feel those
connections like that this is a a
a good chance this would be a real
outcome. This is the implicit 90%
unavoidable. And if it's avoidable, it
would be something else in terms of
specificity, but still sharing pretty
much the same nature. Separation,
disgust, aging, loss of senses. All of
those are implicit things that are
unavoidable and they are not a problem
for as long as you're not dependent on
the senses.
And how you're dependent on the senses?
Well, through having sense desires
unchecked, growing, proliferating,
becoming your mode of being as the mode
of the only way of knowing how to escape
the pain,
that's when those things become a
problem. So you realize, okay, so before
I engage with these things, if I always
have the context of the implicit outcome
of my own senses, for example, which is
kind of immediate and delayed at the
same time, the implication can be
recognized on both levels. That's
already enough to like oh a sense of
danger of going down this path and then
you can refine it further and further to
any extent to match any extent the
desire or pressure arises. If it's a lot
course give it a broad one. If it's a
subtle pushes well match them to that
level. But the point is the mind needs
to understand it. The mind needs to
penetrate it through and through.
And that's not going to happen through
the mere practice of just think about
something else. Don't think about the
future. Just stop thinking. Stop
thinking. Concentrate. Now the
techniques and stuff that's just like
completely uh as I said obscures it even
further because you you're you're reinforcing
because you you're you're reinforcing
the view that the problem was in those
phenomena not in your own desire. An
untrained mind that's remains like even
like well it becomes even worse now like
you're not even seeing it. uh and any
chance to see it now has been buried
even deeper through through engaging in
in developing further these these wrong
views that become further and further
fetterss and increasing of the
obstacles.
Um so it's like
yeah oh yeah so somebody did say um sent
that uh it's quite a good suta like um
just that adds to this
um
this whole kind of practice we described
like with both sutas together really
like recognition that sense desires
um are an issue and even if you say I
don't want to be a monk I don't want to
train for enlightenment
uh that still doesn't mean you should
just completely keep your desires
unchecked. It will still benefit you
even in this life let alone like you
know the subsequent lives and so on. Um
but the point is yeah so when people
hear that the sensuality
the problem of it say
say say say say say say say say say say
say they not necessarily finding faults
by default they're not necessarily
saying oh no this is not a problem like
like these you know the three types of
people which by the way it wasn't like
uh it was common back in the Buddhist
day as well and that's what this person
sent the suta saying like um yeah when
the majima 75 five when um when he
called the Buddha the he's the destroyer
of growth. So he was trying to disparage
the Buddha. By disparaging the Buddha,
you then disparage everything that he
tells you you need to do for liberation.
And he says, "Well, what do you mean by
destroyer of growth? Do you mean that
the eye that delights in forms, takes
delight in forms, rejoices in forms, has
been tamed by tatagata, has been
subdued, guarded, protected, restrained?
that that the target teaches the dharma
for the purpose of restraint of the
senses is the reference to that what you
said that reclus goautam is destroyer of
growth and he said yeah yeah yeah that's
that's why we call you destroyer of
growth because you're telling us to
practice sense restraint basically
you're destroyer of growth you're
destroyer of the of the nature of the
right things or whatever basically just
trying to to disparage him
uh so to not have to do it
so it's Okay, you don't go that far. You
don't disparage the Buddha. You don't
disparage like don't disparage maybe
people when or or even like what you
read or hear. See that's another thing
like for example like say you never
heard that sensuality is a problem and
then you come across it you heard it
somebody told you or you read a book or
something it didn't cross your mind
before that might be like a real
scenario but then it now it did. What do
you do now? What do you do now when you
heard about it?
Like, do you automatically go into
defense mode? Ah, who does he think he
is? No, he doesn't know what he's
talking about. Oh, he's a destroyer of
growth. Oh, he's a fanatic. Whatever
names you want to call, it's like that's
already a level increasing the level of
dishonesty because all of that now is
rooted in an obvious irrational
uh mechanism of self-defense. Who are
you to say that? It doesn't matter. Even
if a person that themselves don't keep
celibacy, don't keep any rules, tell you
that celibacy is beneficial.
They're still right.
That's even the Buddha said that they're
like people that encourage others to do
right things and they do it themselves.
That's great. Then you have the ones
that encourage others to do the same
things, but they don't do it themselves.
But it's still great that they encourage
others. And then you have ones that
don't encourage other and they don't do
it themselves. They're the worst.
Because again if you're an honest
transparent person
even if I say a person who doesn't keep
no rules no precepts nothing tells you
about it and would be easy to dismiss
because look at them how are they
behaving it's like but that's not my
concern my concern is to like genuinely
like take what I heard now
and see like hold on so why is my mind
immediately resisting this? Sure, even
if maybe somebody proves to me later on
that yeah, look, sensuality was not an
obstacle, which obviously it's
impossible, but say for the argument
sake, somebody can prove to you that
sense desires are not an obstacle later
on. Now you don't know that. All you
know now is that when you think about
sense restraint, the mind kicks and
screams. When you think about sense
restraint, the aversion comes up. blame
those who told me, disparage them,
or oh, I'll just cover this whole thing
up and say, "No, that's not true." And
and leave it there. Not really
understand why is that not true or
understand why it's true. So, if you're
an honest person, even if hearing like a
a third, fourth person's account about
it, if you're honest person, you would
be taking that on philosophically. What
if this is true?
What does that result in?
What does what does that make my mind
do? And then you, as I said, like even
if somebody gives you an answer an
isolated whatever in regard to
sensuality, you realize that that's all
secondary for you here and now. The
problem is that the mind resists a mere
hypothetical scenario of saying no to
the desires. That's an acute problem
now. And that should concern you.
Not like I must become celibate and
perfectly restrained overnight or
something or I must have the ultimate
authority prove to me that sense desires
are bad before I give them up. All of
that becomes secondary. What's primary
is that even merely hearing about it,
your mind resists and you you you're
overwhelmed by it or you don't want to
deal with it or you don't recognize that
as a problem. So and that's the whole
point of like when people you know
people that develop the right view
became sapana and said even if the whole
world comes and says everything the
Buddha said was wrong
you know that that's that cannot be
correct because you would have verified
for yourself where the problem was.
So somebody said oh sense desires are
bad after the initial panic initial name
calling initial fault finding you said
okay but even if they're bad or not bad
the point is why did my mind right
simply by hearing that reject the idea
so much surely I should investigate that
surely I should maybe hey come back here
let's work with this regardless of what
answer in regard to sensuality we get
I want you to not be
so affected, so overwhelmed, so panicked
when you hear about the precipice of
sense restraint.
And then when that's developed, let's
take it further and think about really
if it's not an obstacle or not. But see,
the fact that the mind already resisted,
that's already an obstacle itself. the
fact that you just go along with it and
you don't want to deal with it and you
want to blame the others or or dismiss
the whole thing or whatever that's an
obstacle. So you already got an
immediate verification that sensuality
is obstacle because saying no to
sensuality there will be there will be
no untrained mind that hasn't practiced
rightly that when they hear about
restraint will prefer it.
will prefer it.
Every single mind when you hear about
restraint will resist it to different
extents, different people, different
amount of dust in their eyes, but they
will not want to do it today at least.
Maybe back in the Buddhist day, they
were ones that immediately leapted upon
um leaped upon the the the opportunity
because they saw the benefit from it.
But naturally today first and foremost
will be resistance of the mind and
that's a problem regardless of say we
find new sutras verified through the
that whatever that laser technology that
they were authentic that yeah the Buddha
said actually sensuality is not that big
a deal it still doesn't matter you would
know that well that did not come from
the Buddha because I verified for myself
that whenever restraint is presented the
mind resists it and resistance of the
mind that I have to follow along is
always an obstacle. It's always a
fetter. It's the root of suffering
by any stretch by any definition. It's
the root of all problems. Untamed mind.
So whatever technical answer you might
find and give through some whatever say
hypothetical for argument sake
scenarios, you still know what's correct
right now because the mind is still
resisting it. If it's tamed, if it's not
uh not panicking, not trying to push you
away from it, great. It's not a problem
either way. But as if you start doing
that, if you take it on that level and
start training, you will very quickly
realize, oh no, this is always a
problem. And there is no other way and
there will be no future answer that will
tell you oh sensuality was never a
problem because you realize that anytime
you engage with it it was through
ignoring the fact that it was problem
through ignoring the fact that animal
was driving you and controlling you
through ignoring the fact that that's
actually bothersome and frightening in
and of itself that lack of control but
you just go along because hey we get
what we want. So then there is no
further second guessing. So you kind of
develop a degree of comfort and and and
um familiarity with it until basically
all it takes is not get what you want,
be separated from what you had and the
whole thing just breaks apart and just
shows you how how how how fickle the
whole setup was. So as I said, if you
actually say even if you're not
convinced by the argument that
sensuality is always a problem and you
see no reason in moderating it, just do
it for the philosh philosophically just
for a philosophy sake for the sake of
understanding it. Hypothetically say
what if just for a week I say no to my
main sensual desires
and see what will that do to your mind
and then really honestly say at the end
of it, oh that's not the problem. The
fact that my mind can turn against me to
such a violent extent with fear and
pressure, that's not a that's surely a
problem. Anybody with any degree of
honesty, with an ounce of transparency,
would would not be able to ignore that
as a problem, as a root of all problems,
the untained mind, untrained one.
>> Yeah. I I had a personal experience
regarding the mind and the situation. So
I was thinking to uh ask uh actually
how I could do this well uh about my
situation. So I had a conflict with my
with my coworker.
>> Uhhuh. Coworker.
>> Coworker. Yes.
>> Uh I mean conflict means like verbal or
like kind of behavioral. So it's like
not fighting, you know.
>> Yeah. Um
and um yes I was uh trying my best to to
think about it um again and again but
automatically my mind was
back like a lof of thoughts are going on
like um I could I could see the the like
a film what could happen and all these
things and you all the time. It's um
bad feeling, angry, not satisfied
what I could do, what uh this person
could do and you know it's kind of
discouraging. So I was I was trying to
avoid these thoughts. So as I listen to
you, it's like u is it uh I was trying
to like focus my thoughts to like for
example when I was uh walking in the I
was like trying to focus my uh steps
rather than thinking what was going on
there. M but uh yeah it was quite
difficult because automatically my mind
was like
>> going again and again
>> like
>> doesn't matter how much you improve your
concentration all that's going to result is result in
all that's going to result is result in
is you becoming more and more precious
about controlling your environment which
means more and more things will then be
triggering of the same same states.
>> So my question is what what should I do
mean I mean the the best way that I
could uh deal with this situation. Well,
>> well, the most immediate thing say it's
like well the most immediate thing
obviously when that when that is
happening is if you're still in that
situation well don't do anything by body
or speech bite your tongue type of thing
doesn't matter the the amount of
pressure and the pain that comes and
then afterwards say when the mind is
just revolving around it uh the point is
uh trying to concentrate away from it
tries to deny the whole state of mind
that's there and
So you can't stop the momentum because
it will take time to start slowing it
down. So in those scenarios when the
mind wants well well basically when you
can't help but think about
direct that to thinking about other
aspects that are not where the mind
wants to go of the same thing by the way
not not completely different. So in your
case, say coworker has said something
and now you walk through a park and the
mind is just rehashing what he said and
what you should have said and what next
time you'll say and then but maybe you
shouldn't but there instead all of that
think about hold on I am walking in the
park now regarding something that
happened before and my mind is burning
the animal is actually burning. Let me
think about the burning animal trying to
get me to act, not what he wants me to
think about.
Cuz that is a factual state of affairs
that's being overlooked
by you following along the lines offered
by the animal.
Because factually the only reason all of
that is a problem
who said what and and next time and this
and and and yesterday and in in five
days uh in the future it's all because
it's unpleasant here and now that state
of the animal and that pain is something
you just want to get rid of. So instead
think about the pain think about the
pain of the animal
like factually like oh hold on I am
working the walking through the park
pressured to think about I know exactly
what what thoughts it will be even
without having to think about them I see
where it's going I see where it's been
repeating the mind's burning I can feel
it I can feel the discomfort and that
thing is really as such experience
really as such that phenomena of that
mind state driving me forcing me trying
to force me to accept these choices
along these lines and think further and
so on and resolve it. That's real as
such. That pressure is real as such and
I'm feeling it. So I can't think about
that cuz that's not what the mind wants
you to think about. Mind wants you to
think about the content, wants to think
about the coworker of who said what and
this and this and this and this and
this. We just increases the desire to
get rid of it. Increases the aversion
increases this increases the whole bond
so to speak increases the feta.
So instead, think about the the say the
the the the the grounds for all of that
that you're going through now. The
grounds that very much is felt most
acutely even more than your fantasy,
even more than the thoughts you're going
through. The fact is the burning mind is
real as such and it's right here and I
can't stop it. Hold on. Am I supposed to
stop it? Is that what the one who
understood the Buddha teaching rightly
would do? Is that what I learned?
Should I just stop this animal now
that's burning or should I contain it?
Should I not follow along the lines or
should I just completely as I said choke
it asphixxiated get rid of it replace it
with a different state of mind? It's
like oh but then I'm still acting out of
the animal. So the main reason people
keep falling into these patterns of like
loops and vicious cycles and not able to
is because they never address the real
thing which is the actual state of mind
right there and then. I mean they know
it obviously you cannot know it you're
feeling it but they go about it in every
possible way except the way of hold on
how about I keep looking at you instead
of what you are offering me to look at.
And even if it's rooted in the same
aversion, it's less inaccurate
it's less inaccurate
than going along the lines, which means
they're going to be less desire uh uh
fettering you, less kind of involvement,
which in return is going to make things
clearer, which in return is going to
make it next time even less inaccurate
and less inaccurate to the point of
you'll be seeing it accurately right
through. But it needs to be an active effort. And
But it needs to be an active effort. And
in this case, as I said, I mean, it's
always an active effort trying to
concentrate away. It's an active effort.
It just falls flat. You concentrate
away, but then 5 seconds later, the mind
is still same
spiral. The only time it stops, it's
after four, five, six hours have passed.
Hopefully, sometimes not even then.
Sometimes three or four days, it still
comes back. So, you realize, oh, okay.
Basically, I am making the effort either way.
I am making the effort either way.
in trying to get rid of it, trying to
concentrate away from it. How about
instead I think about the real source of
the issue here,
reflect on it, ask questions about it,
everything. Just don't go along the
offered lines of thought. That's it.
It's like, do I need to get rid of it?
No. So, why am I trying to get rid of
it? Well, I don't know. Cuz I I forgot
that I don't have to get rid of it. So,
what if this state of mind stays for the
rest of the day? But me not fueling it,
I don't need to do anything.
There is no right thing I could have
said or I should have said. All of that
is fueled by the pain that the burning
mind puts on you and you take for
granted as something that I must deal
with and then you overlook the level where
and then you overlook the level where
you can deal with it and you think that
dealing with it is our practice, my um
communication skills or something. so
that this will be prevented in the
future. It's like you're still not
dealing with it here and now. You're
addressing the future. The phenomena
that pertains to the future that is
basis for desire and lust as we just
described. That's what you're
addressing. You're not addressing desire
last right now.
So instead of falling into the trap or
when you fall into trap and you
recognize you could like oh hold on I
have fallen into a trap. The burning
mind pushed me into it. I didn't see it.
Is it still burning? Yes. Is it still
unpleasant? Yes. Do I need to do
anything about it? Well, I have a strong
urge, but I don't have to do anything
about it. How about I make the effort of
not doing anything about it, but not
losing the sight of it either, which is
already a form of doing something about
it, just not on your own terms, not on
the terms that are infused with with
lust and craving and that vicious cycle.
So, you can use the same momentum
against the mind. Instead of thinking
the content that it offers, you think
about the state of mind, the pressure,
the the the unpleasantness of it, how
unbeneficial it is to not have it
trained when something so trivial
can disrupt it so much. It's like, oh
no, you are the problem. Not the
colleague, not what I said, not what I
should have said, [gasps] not be not
now, not me refusing to think with what
you're what you want me to think. And
then mind tries to pressure. None of
that's the problem. You are the problem.
You're the problem that you're still
capable of such upset, of such lust, of
such desire, of such force. That's the
problem. And I need to keep an eye on it
because that's how I begin taming it.
And then for as long as the momentum
last for as long that long you use the
momentum to think about the mind that's
pushing you into that momentum. That's
really again it's not an abstract thing
because it's going to be felt very much
so. Oh, where's my mind? Where is this
animal? It's right there where that pain
is. That is what the mind is.
So it's like oh this pain is the mind
here and now in in practical terms don't
get all technical the practical terms
it's what the mind is. It's what stands
for the mind most accurately there and
then affected with aversion affected
with lust with all the implications that
it has. It's like ahuh so you are the
problem.
I can't get rid of it. I can't just
remove the mind, not have it.
Well, if you never read the sutras or
listened to our talks, you would say, I
don't really know what to do. But you
heard so many times, so you know what to
do. Like you have the information.
Oh, you are the problem. I shall not
fuel it, but I shall not try to deny you
either. I will recognize you as the
problem. And then when you're not a problem, I
And then when you're not a problem, I
will recognize you as not a problem.
And then stay with it. And whenever it
comes up the trigger or whatever, you
like it's the mind that's the trigger,
not the specific thoughts that feels
like prompted you and made you feel this
or made you feel that. No, no. It's the
animal. Is the animal still being
touchy, still being twitchy, still being
liable to these things? So, by seeing
the animal, you already kind of dealt
with 50% of the problem, which is not
seeing the animal and falling into the
loops. It's not going to be perfect. As I said,
It's not going to be perfect. As I said,
you're going to fall into loose and
catch yourself. But whenever you catch
yourself, you don't double down. I must
try harder to concentrate away from the
whole thing and shut my mind. No, I must
try harder to not lose the corner of my
eye from the pressuring problem here and
now, which is the state of chitta,
[snorts] the soul problem always. There
was never any other problem in your
life. It was always the state of chitta
affected with only three things. Greed,
aversion or distraction. There is no
fourth. Just these three things always
on that level. And I always keep saying
that because it always ties into
everything. It's like that suta when
when they ask the Buddha, "Oh, you said
dama is directly visible here and now.
How is it so?" And you would think oh
because you concentrate on a subatomic
particle of the you know multitude of
your insight of some secret hidden
dimensions. It's like no dhamma is
visible here and now when you know mind
of lust as mind of lust. In other words
when you have not fallen into a trap or
follow along the lines got distracted
got lost or acted out even worse. When
you know mind of aversion is mind of
aversion. Mind of distraction mind of
distraction. Like when you know the state of mind for
Like when you know the state of mind for
what is when you see it aha I see you.
That's you are the issue. You reacting
to this this way that way sometimes like
this that's you are the problem. Your
lack of tameness lack of um your desires
the dependence on desire. You are the
problem. And that's how you see the
dharma here and now directly visible.
Even if you had no instruction in dharma
whatsoever, you are practicing along the
dharma. [snorts]
Which means again you would be
developing rightly.
Yeah, thank you very much. Uh actually
yeah when the pressure is so strong I
think it constantly
uh like avoid me to focus exactly I mean
to identify the mind always go back to
the scenario and you know is
>> yeah so basically the pressure is making
you focus on things the mind wants you
focused and then the best the person can
do is let me focus on something else
just just focus just forget about this
but that does not teach the find the
right things. So instead of focusing,
unabsorb yourself. When when the
momentum is trying to get you boiled
down to the specifics,
don't focus on that. Unfocus yourself
from the specifics to basically refill
the state of mind that's already felt
and stay on that level of being
unabsorbed to the momentum that's trying
to absorb you.
>> Thank you.
Welcome.